Hi, my name is Elena.
I'm senior performance engineer at
SAP, and, I have special love for
front-end JavaScript, browser APIs.
And today I want to talk about, browser
security policies, but, browser security
policies from, developer points of
view, when, Those policies, break,
our perfectly, working, JavaScript.
when we're talking about, browser security
policies, we usually, discuss how to
making them the most secure, how to make
sure that, they stop as many, possible
vulnerabilities and, attacks as possible.
but today I want to ask,
a different question.
I want to ask, how do we make
sure that our, code, stays,
compatible with, those policies?
And, this question comes
from, my working experience.
for the last few years I've been
working on, SDK that our customers
embed into our, into their, pages.
And, so we don't really control the
environment, where our JavaScript
runs, and we cannot, really
test, our code and integration
with, customer security policies.
So we need, to try and make
sure, to catch these issues
as early as, we possibly, can.
Of course, if you do own the environment
and, your team actually can test
everything, beforehand, you may
ask why does it even matter to you?
And that's a great question, and
I have a few answers for that.
first, catching any issue as early
as possible is always cheaper, and
it doesn't, then require rewrites
and, rethinking, the approach.
Also, not every flow can be tested and,
with, browser security policies it's
actually, very important, to catch the
bug in the specific flow because, for
example, if we take a content security
policy that, blocks eval, it doesn't mean
that a browser will scan the, the script,
see eval there, and, fully, block the
script even though it would be probably
much easier to catch a, an issue then.
But instead it will, block eval in
the moment of execution, which means,
that, some untested flow can introduce
the bug that we'll just not, catch.
And also, of course, we have more and
more, AI-generated code, and so it's
important to have some, constraints
in place to, make sure that, the
codes that, is vulnerable or just
not in, not aligned with our security
policies will, not, be even committed.
let's, look now at, an example
of something that, just breaks
because of the security policy.
so let's say we have, we have
this, login, with, pop-up, right?
So we log in a pop-up, using
third-party authentication provider.
So we click Sign In.
the pop-up is open.
I click Continue.
I'm logged in, and everything is great.
And, maybe it will, work, for
a few months or even a few
years, I don't know, 10 years.
but then, one day, you get the
bug that it's not working anymore.
So we click Sign In as we did before,
and as before, I click Continue.
but nothing happens.
I get stuck in this weird state,
and, login didn't happen, and the
pop-up didn't close, and there
are no, errors in console, right?
we can see that there is nothing here.
So what, what could actually break?
probably after a few, hours or even a
few days of testing, you will finally
f- discover that, the page of, the
third-party provider that you're using
is, has added this, header called,
Cross-Origin-Opener-Policy, which
basically severs the connection between
the pop-up and, the parent window.
so if, we actually, type window
opener in the console, we will see
that it's not, available anymore.
It's just, null, even though it's
something that was, used, before
when everything was working, and,
it was actually, available So let's
look at what, happened here and,
what could we do to prevent it.
So here we have, my site,
my parent window, and we
start authentication process.
We call window open, and we, open a
third-party, provider in our popup.
And then, here we click log in, and we
get redirected back to our, site's, URL,
but still, still in the same popup window.
And here we were using window
opener postMessage to communicate
to the parent window, that, login
happened, maybe, send, a token and
afterwards, just close the popup.
And, when we add this
crossOriginOpenerPolicy to
the, authentication provider's
page, it basically makes window
opener, not available anymore.
And so this connection between, popup
and parent window, doesn't exist anymore.
so
The question is, what was the issue
here and what assumpt- assumptions
did we make, during the design?
the assumption was that the pop-up will
always have access to window opener, and,
the header that was added by, provider
has actually, broken this assumption, and
maybe the assumption was even, correct
for the most cases like, many years ago,
but it's not, correct anymore because,
security issues are tightening, and we
learn more and more about, different
vulnerabilities and how to prevent them.
and so now when we're working about,
working with, browser APIs, really
introducing any, browser API to our, code,
we need to first ask a few questions.
does this API depend on a relationship
between, windows, right pop-ups,
maybe, on specific origins?
can a security header, block this code?
does-- can this code only run
in secure context like HTTPS?
maybe permission policy can restrict it.
after asking these questions, we may
decide to, change our design completely.
For example, in this specific case, we
could say that, we don't, want to use
pop-up at all, even though in some cases
it may be better UX, and instead we would
use, authentication, using redirect.
And so it will completely, eliminate
this issue with the pop-up.
Or we could say that, we could research
and say, we will use instead, a
window broadcast that doesn't rely
on the opener and, also that can also
prevent, this issue from happening.
and of course, to answer these questions,
you would also-- you would usually
go to MDN, to the recommendation for
the APIs, and, it can be also a good
step to incorporate, these questions,
into, your work with AI agents and
maybe, for example, use, MDN MCP.
from what I saw, it's still in experiment-
experimental phase, but it still
already can, help you to answer the
questions about APIs that you're using
and to make sure that you're not just,
relying on, models', hallucinations.
Now, during our development process,
we also want to introduce some,
deterministic, checks that may prevent,
us from using, some APIs that we are
sh- that we shouldn't be using or,
using it in the way that we shouldn't.
of course, A part of this job is, done by,
security scanners, but they cannot catch
everything that we're talking about here.
Instead, it's great to have,
a few mechanisms, in place
to, catch possible issues.
And I won't be touching much, security
scanners, because they are already part
of most, pipelines, and they're doing
their job great, and I just want to
talk about, different mechanisms that we
can have, in place in addition to that.
so one thing that we can do is we
can, use, static, code, scanning
for, catching some issues.
here as an example I will be using,
ESLint, just because it's something that,
many JavaScript and TypeScript, projects
already have, and it's, something that's,
often underutilized and, it's, used,
maybe only for, catching some, code style
issues, but it can do much more than that.
And, it can prevent us from having,
some other issues, including, security
issues and just, incompatibility
with, some, browser security policies.
let's look into, some of them.
first, one thing that we can, do
out of the box, very cheap with
ESLint is to block, eval forever.
if you're not, familiar…
not very familiar with JavaScript, eval is
basically a function that can, ex- execute
any JavaScript that is given to it.
So it can be easily exploited to, execute
some malicious JavaScript, and then…
So we always, want to ban it of course.
And, ESLint just gives it for free.
and it, allows you to ban,
different notations, for eval.
It's, the eval itself.
It's also, the new function notation,
which, essentially the same as eval
and just, can, execute any JavaScript.
And another notation that can
happen is, setTimeout with, a string
parameter instead of the function,
which essentially will also, execute
JavaScript, given to it as a string.
we want to, avoid this, them, and we can
just, add, these rules to ESLint and,
we, already get this one, restriction
for free we can also, blocked, block or
restrict, specific functions that we want.
eval is something that is, already built
in, ESLint, but we also can, basically
forbid, using any, function, or we can…
or, property a- assignment, or
we can, say that we only want
to use it in some specific ways.
for example, we can say that
we don't want to, we can…
that we want to fully forbid innerHTML
from being used, in our JavaScript.
or we can say that we want to, use it
only with, some sanitization function.
by the way, when I'm talking about
innerHTML, there are some other similar
functions like outerHTML and, or,
assignments and insertJSON into HTML
and a few others, that, basically,
can cause the same vulnerability,
the same, issue where we just assign,
an HTML to, our page and that it can
have, some, malicious, script inside.
so I have just an example
here of, how, it can be done.
We can use an ESLint, no restricted
syntax, and we can say here that we
don't want to have inner and outerHTML.
again, there are, like, more, things
that we need to restrict, but, just
for example, we have these two.
So we are saying that we don't want to
have innerHTML or outerHTML without,
sanitizeHTML, function used with them.
And, let's, actually look at the
live example of how it works.
so I have, two files here.
In one I just perform assignment of,
innerHTML, without any sanitization.
And I have another, file,
where we actually do have,
sanitization, as you can see.
Have innerHTML, and then
we have sanitizeHTML.
So it's actually sanitized.
And we have, the rule in our ESLint,
which, says exactly what we just,
discussed, that we don't want to see
innerHTML, without, without, sanitization
So now, we can, run, our linter, and
we can see that we will get exactly
one error that says that we only want
to write markup with, sanitize, HTML
function, which is, exactly, what we want.
innerHTML, is, a security violation
or it is concern by itself.
And now, there is a thing called
trusted types that, in this year,
became, available in, modern browsers.
And, it can be enforced by,
kind of security policy.
And th- then, innerHTML
not just becomes the…
something, dangerous, but b- it
becomes something that actually can
be blocked by content security policy.
So it, can be important, always
important, but even more important
to, pay attention to that.
So let's look what else can
we, do with our, ESLint rules.
let's say that we, want, to
forbid our, application to u-
to use worker with, a blob.
And, like the usual security policies,
CSP headers will actually, restrict
this usage unless we explicitly
allow a worker, with a blob.
So we want to make sure that, this
code, where we use, create new worker
with the blob will not, happen.
And, first, we could just say that
we completely forbid, create object
URL, in our, application if we
don't use it for any other cases,
and it will, may be good enough.
but if we don't want to forbid
it, we need to understand that
this, creation URL can even come
from, different, different files.
So it may be not as easy as saying
to just, "I w- don't want to,
call worker with a URL create
object URL as a parameter," right?
what can we do here is, we can say
that we have some, worker factory
or some file that, creates, workers.
And it's, it is the only file that
is allowed to, call new worker,
and it owns worker URL creation.
And it exposes some method that can be
used, by other, files, to create a worker.
And all the other files are only are
allowed, to use, create worker function,
and they're actually not allowed
to call a new worker, explicitly so
it lowers, the chance significantly
that, we will, introduce, some block
worker in- a blob worker in our code,
or maybe I will introduce it because
it's, concentrated in one file.
Of course, there is also a possibility
that, there will be some issue there,
but, it's much easier to avoid if
it's all concentrated, in one file.
we can also, use it, for example,
going back to our first, example, we
can say that we don't want to use,
window open i- in our app anymore,
or we want to use a window open
o- only when it's, called with, no
opener, no referrer as, parameters.
we can also, say that we want to allow,
using fetch only, with, specific, URLs,
so it can be done in similar fashion
to what we discussed, with worker
now Also, ESLint doesn't necessarily
have to fully forbid APIs, but it
can just, warn you about, some APIs.
So you may want to decide that you, want
to get a warning about some specific,
functions, being used, which can also,
save you from, some issues later.
So again, there…
you can use different tools, but, even
ESLint have, much more capabilities than
just, checking, code, code quality in
terms of, in terms of, code style, rules.
now let's, look at something else.
let's say that we added rules
in our ESLint config that,
will, protect us, from eval.
And the question is, are we now safe
from eval in our, production code?
And for, a lot of time, I thought
that, yes, we are safe, but, it
turned out that, there can be an, an
additional source of, such issues.
so let's, look at the example.
let's say that we have, this code
where we have eval and new function,
and we finally, rewrote it, and we
don't have, eval anymore, in this code.
So now we will also run lint, and we
will see that we, don't have any issues
here, and it's, completely clear.
now we will open the page, and we
will see that it's, for some reason,
not working And we can see here that
we have a eval error, and it means
that, there is content security
policy that blocks, eval on our page.
but we just saw that we don't
have eval, so what have happened?
so it, turns out, that even though we
don't have eval in our source code,
we do have, some interesting, webpack,
setting, for source maps that is…
that starts with eval, and it
basically it's eval, to modules.
And so eval, even though it's not
in the source code, and eventually
ends up, being in your build.
So that, can also introduce,
eval into your, code that
eventually will, run on your site.
Now, we can see that if we actually,
stop using this rule, we will
see that our, page, will work as
expected and it now loads, and
there, there is no error about eval.
what can we do here?
we can do a couple of things.
first, just knowing about that,
already protects us from some of these
issues because, now we pay much more
attention about, to our config and
what options, we include in our config.
because if you never ran into
this, kind of issue, you may
really be surprised by that.
Another thing that we can do, we can
actually, write, linter that will,
forbid some, specific, settings from
being used in our, in our webpack config
or in general in our bundler config.
So here we can say that, we don't
want to have, devtool, property with,
any values that starts, with eval.
And now if we actually run the linter,
we can see that we, get an error
here that, forbids us from using it.
Of course, eval source maps and, such
settings, they're not, they're not,
supposed to be used on production,
but, there's also nothing, stopping us,
from it unless we decide that we want
to have additional, checks for that.
So it can end up, there if
we're not careful, we just need
to know that it can happen.
And another thing that we can do is
we can actually, like usually when we
are, scanning our code for security,
or linting our code, we, lint our,
source code, which makes a lot of
sense, but may also, be worth it to
add a really thin scanner for the build
that will make sure that- that there
is, no eval, maybe no, blob, no, data
attribute, and, it can also be helpful,
in, saving us from some issues, later.
of course, Webpack is not the only
bundler that can introduce it.
Wi- Vite can also introduce, some things.
And, so in general, just, important
to, pay attention to what happens
in your, bundler config and, what
ends up, not only in the source
cod- code, but, in the build.
some things that can, appear there is
eval, of course, inline styles that
can also, be a security vulnerability,
dynamic scripts that can also be
blocked by common security policies in,
specific cases, and, some blob and data
resources that can also be blocked, and
also can be, security vulnerabilities.
we can fully restrict them, and we can
also pay attention to our config, and,
make sure that we avoid the things that
we don't want to end up in our build.
and, just to recap that we can, lint
the config itself for some issues,
especially if they once already happened.
We want to make sure they don't want…
they don't, happen anymore.
or we can scan the build artifact
for, these few, things that
can, end up, in the build.
And now let's talk about, testing.
so in general, of course, we can
just, test things in our, staging
test environment and make sure
that everything, works fine.
but sometimes, browser security
policies can be, different, for
example, on production and on staging.
And, we want to make sure that tests,
always run with, specific, a specific,
policies and that we actually know for
sure with which policies this, test run.
So using, testing config, we can actually,
run the same tests, with, different,
security configurations and regardless
of the environment and make sure that
we don't need to, change settings
for, environment every time that we
want to maybe test different settings.
Also, during the tests, we can collect,
security violations and, see if there are
any and, understand why they happened.
And we also, w- we are also able
to actually, to actually make
sure that things that we expect to
fail, with our economic security
pol- policies, will actually fail.
so I will be using, Playwright
as an example just, because it's
something that I usually, use.
here we can, provide, two…
we can create two different projects,
with different settings, and one will
have, as we can see here, more permissive,
CSP header that allows a worker, to
use a blob, and we can have another
more strict policy that, disallows it.
And, CSP is the sh- is the something
that I decided to provide, right?
You can provide anything,
inside, the use object.
And then
And then, inside before each or inside
of fixture, we can actually, now use,
this value that we provided for CSP
for this, object, and we can, eh,
add additional, header that will,
have our content security policy.
In this way we'll be also-- we will
always, be sure that our tests actually
run with the policy, that we want.
right?
So this is something that,
we can add, to our tests.
And, inside, before each or fixture,
we can also, observe, eh, the reports,
the, security violation reports, and,
we can, then attach them as annotations
to our, test cases, so then when we
see the report, we will actually,
see the failures, that, happened.
let's look at an example.
here we have a test that,
checks that, work around some
of the policy of this project.
probably in real life you will just have
the test that, tests actual functionality
that, you can make sure that works.
And here we have just a function
that, adds a security header.
It also attaches, security violation
reports, to our annotations.
probably also in real life, project,
this, logic will be in the fixture,
but, just, made it like this
for, simplicity and visibility.
we have this test.
now let's run it and see what will
happen, with, different, policies.
So first we'll run with,
more, permissive, policy
Right?
So here we can see that, this
is the one that enables blob
And the test run, we see that
the worker has actually, replied.
And now if we will look at the report,
we can see that the test has passed
and everything as we have expected.
Now let's, run with a strict policy.
By the way, you can see here that I
just, run it with, a different project
names, and the test itself is, the same.
Here I have, project
permissive and project strict
So now I'm running with the
strict policy And we see that
browser has, refused the worker.
And now, We can also look at the report.
And we will see that, report, has
actually, In the report, we can see that,
our test has actually failed, and we
also see an annotation that says exactly
what, viol- CSP violation has happened.
Of course, the annotation, formats
and, in general how you record the,
failures, you can control them yourself.
It's just, one of the
examples how it can be done.
So here you can see the test failed,
and you can also see the violation
Now another example of,
what we can actually test.
let's say that our, we decided that our
page, should not be embedded inside the
iframe, inside any iframe, and, we want
to check if it will actually, if the
embedding will, fail, on production.
here just, again as an example, we can
see that our strict policy, includes,
frame ancestors none which means that our
page, cannot be, embedded into the iframe
And now our test actually checks
that the page allows inside iframe
under the policy of this project.
But, we expect this test, to fail,
because we don't want to, because we
don't want it to be embedded, right?
And, we expect it to fail
only for the strict project
that has, the stricter policy.
And, let's, run this, test
and see what will happen
So first, let's run it
with, a permissive policy
So we see that the iframe
was actually loaded and
We can also see that, the test has passed
and we don't have any, any violations.
Everything looks as expected.
now I want to run it with strict policy
where we do not allow our page to be
part of iframe, and we can see that
indeed it was not, loaded as we expected.
And now if we look at the report,
we can see that even though we have
violation here and we have a failure
here, we still see that the test is
passed because that's exactly what
we have, expected, under this, strict
policy that the test will fail.
from the report standpoint of view,
it actually has passed because it's
the expected behavior and it can be
re- really useful to see what actually
happens in your production under…
And if your header is actually, doing
the job and if there are still there,
maybe this specific, usage of, fail
can be even more useful, with, the
real policy that you have on a specific
environment Of course, we looked at
we can have, different policies as,
part of, configuration, as part of,
different, Playwright projects, but we
also can have a project that doesn't
have any additional configuration and
just runs with the security headers
that actually part of the environment
where the tests are running on.
I just want to quickly
touch on something else.
this is already, something that we can
do on production to actually monitor
our, security violations, specifically,
content security policy, CRP permission
policy, some, browser API deprecations.
we can, use, report only, security
headers to make sure that our
violations actually reported, and we
can actually, see what happens on our
page so it may look something like this.
You, define your reporting endpoints,
and then, in the, security header,
you define, where to report to.
Here we report to the
default reporting endpoints.
And as, we discussed, on the
previous slide, it's not only
security, common security policy
that we can actually, catch.
just important to remember here that, this
endpoint where we send our reports, is an
actual public endpoint that is available
to everyone, so we need to have, security
checks in place, to make sure that, we
don't store any malicious data, that it's
not overloaded with some huge requests.
yeah, just important to remember And
they can be used, to, test, some,
for example, more strict policy that
we want to, roll out and, we want to
see that, it will not break anything.
Or we can, leave them alongside with
our, usual, security policy to, make sure
that we, even after the policy's rolled
out, we still, get the reports about,
violations, that happen on, the page.
so this is how our, report, may look like.
depending on the, depending
on the violation, it can have
or not have different fields.
It's also important to remember that
some URLs can have some, sensitive
information like, I don't know, some
tokens that we don't want to store.
so it's important to also, to
also check what you're actually
storing and don't, store all the
data that you have on the reports
So we also, can, do some
monitoring if we, don't have
access, to changing the headers.
mostly if we, own some third-party
script that customers, use, we don't…
w- we are not able to, set
our header, their headers.
so instead we can use, Security Policy
Violation API or Reporting Observer
API, to, monitor, the viol- the security
violations that happen on their pages.
of course, there are some,
differences between them.
Security Policy Violation is, CSP
specific, and it only, captures the
reports, that, or violations that happen
after it was installed on the page.
and Reporting Observer, supports,
multiple report types, and it also
can capture reports, reports that were
created even before the observer, starts.
but, Security Policy Violation is,
broadly supported, and Reporting
Observer is a newer API that, may
not be supported at least for all
the types and all the browsers.
So it's important to be aware of
that and, check the actual, support.
anyway, reporting through
the headers is, recommended.
It's more reliable.
for example, if your script doesn't
load at all, of course you will not
know, this from inside the observer
that you added inside the script.
So header is always preferable, but if
you don't have ability to use them, you
can, rely on these APIs, for, reporting.
So I basically went over everything
that I wanted to, cover today.
Just let's do a quick recap
and then finish this talk.
first, during the design phase, we
want to make sure that we ask, what
assumptions, the APIs, that we use
actually make, and, maybe rethink the
design or at least, be aware of, possible
issues that it can cause, in the future.
And during the developments, we can,
block unsafe browser APIs, or we can
block, block specific, ways of how, of
how these APIs are, used in our code.
And we can introduce, some,
architecture constraints with, static
analysis tools, for example, I showed
with ESLint in this presentation.
during the build stage, we can also,
make sure that our, configuration doesn't
introduce any additional, security,
concerns or violations, or discrepancies
with our, browser security policies.
And first it's just important
to be aware of that.
And, we can introduce, some scans for the
bundler configs themselves, or we can add
some thin, scanners for, build artifacts
and not only for, the source code.
we can, use the testing stage to make sure
that, we run our tests, with different
security policies and, we are sure
with which policy our tests, have run.
And we can also, track the
violations, security violations
that, happened during the tests.
And finally, we can use report-only,
headers, or we can use, reports and
observer API to actually monitor, the
violations that happen on, production.
that was all.
thank you very much, for listening.
I have a hope, that you found this
talk, helpful, and maybe you learned
something new or something that you
can use, in your development process.
you can, find the examples from this code
in the GitHub link that you can see here.
Also, if you have any questions, you
can contact me, on LinkedIn, and I just,
added a couple of additional links that
I mentioned, earlier in the slide, so
you will be able to, find them, here.
thank you very much and, have a great day.